A Guide to the Dr. Francis Smith Nash Papers, 1849-1968
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Dr. Francis Smith Nash Papers, 1849-1968 (bulk 1882-1922)
Library of Virginia
28467
1.8 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of B. I. Johns, 1200 N. Quaker Lane, Alexandria, Virginia 22302, 1 April 1974.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Smith Nash was born on 23 November 1854 near Cartersville, Cumberland County, Virginia, to John White and Lydia Maria (Smith) Nash. He received his undergraduate degree from Hampden-Sydney in 1875 and his medical degree from the University of Virginia in 1877. On 22 December 1877, he was commissioned an assistant surgeon in the United States Navy. He married Caroline Louise Ryan, the daughter of William King and Martha Aurelia (Blockwell) Ryan of Charleston, South Carolina, on 15 February 1887. The marriage produced one child, Caroline Ryan Nash, born 17 January 1888.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1849-1968 (bulk 1882-1922), including abstracts, correspondence, deeds, family histories, lists of Revolutionary War and War of 1812 soldiers, marriage bonds, newspaper articles and clippings, notes, publications, and primarily relating to the genealogical study of the Nash and related families. Families represented include: Astor, Bedford, Bransford, Clarke, Cocke, Cowles, Crump, Harris, Hatcher, Hawes, James, Legrand, Poore, Read, Sampson, Smith, White, and Woodson.
Also includes articles, naval orders, and writings relating to Dr. Francis Smith Nash's naval career.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Genealogical Correspondence, 1882-1968; II. Genealogical Notes; III. Personal; IV. Publications; V. Documents.
Contents List
- Genealogical Correspondence, 1882-1968
  - 1882, 1883, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mar., July - Aug. 1888 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sept. 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oct. - Nov. 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1-14 Dec. 1888 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 16-31 Dec. 1888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jan. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Feb. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mar. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1-3 Apr. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 5-30 Apr. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - May 1889 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - June - Sept. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oct. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nov. - Dec. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mar. - May 1890 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - June - Nov. 1890 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1891-1893 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1894-1897 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1905-1912 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1914 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1 May 1968 (Notes from "The Reads and their Relatives" by Alice Read Rouse) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Genealogical Reply Cards (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Postal Receipts (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Forms for Nash's Lineage" (sent and returned to Dr. F. S. Nash, ca. 1888-1889) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Genealogical Notes
  - Ancestral tablets (8)
  - Cowles Family (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hatcher-Clarke-Woodson Families (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Frederick Hatcher (Will, Cumberland County Revolutionary Committee) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nash Legrand (Bulletin of Hampden-Sidney College, Aug. 1922, p. 21) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Major Benjamin H. Nash (1835-1895) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Judge John White Nash (1792 or 1794-1859) and Family (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dr. John White Nash, Jr. (1826-1899) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - John White Nash, III (1857-1880) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nash Family of Prince Edward County (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Nash Coat of Arms and Explanation from Burke's "General Armory" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nash Family of Buckingham County, Va., Marion County, Ky., and Dallas County, Tex., 1772-1888 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sampson Family, Harris Family, Cocke Family (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Smith and Hawes Family Register from 1650 to 1888" (compiled in 1888 ) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Smith Family of "Montrose"; James Family; Bedford Family; Poore Family; Smith Family - Appendix I (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "John Smith of Milford, New Haven Colony, 1840... " by Robert Atwater Smith (reprinted from N. England Historical and Genealogical Register for July 1891 ) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - White Family (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notes (I) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notes (II) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notes (III) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notes (IV) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notes (V) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Source Notes: Hening, William and Mary Quarterly, etc. (3 envelopes) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs - Joseph Nash and family of Colorado; Thomas Cowles; C. W. Bradford (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Personal
  - Naval Orders and Related Correspondence, 21 May 1888 - 14 Feb. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Marriage Announcement - Dr. Francis Smith Nash and Caroline Louise Ryan (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Application Forms - Patriotic Societies (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Hampden-Sidney Magazine, Dec. 1894 (Alumni notes re. Frank Smith Nash, p. 107) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Alumni Bulletin of the University of Virginia, July 1894 (reference to F. S. Nash, p. 31) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chi Phi Chakett, Feb. 1895 (article re. Dr. Francis Smith Nash, p. 108-111) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Military Surgeon, Dec. 1910 (photograph of F. S. Nash, p. 690-691) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Military Surgeon, "Some Elementrary Suggestions Regarding Plans for Our Large Naval Hospitals," Feb. 1911 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Reminiscences--Medical and Hygienic--of the Arctic" (reprinted from Virginia Medical Semi-Monthly, Aug. 13, 1897) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Publications
  - Ancestral Leaflets and Genealogical and Historical Book Catalogs and Notices, ca. 1889 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - American Ancestry, Vol. III, 1888; Virginia Historical Society and Southern Historical Society Notices (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Baptist Review (Goldsboro, NC.), 1 Dec. 1888 (Vol. III, No. 23) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Colorado Index (Colorado Springs, Co.), 18 May 1889 (Vol. XV, No. XXXV) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Critic, n.d. (columns of family histories) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Critic, n.d. ("Genealogical Letters") (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Critic, n.d. ("The Land Patents") (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Critic, n.d. ("The Early Virginia Stage") (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Critic, n.d. ("English Pedigrees of Virginia Families, Notes, and Queries") (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Farmville Journal, 1889-1890 (Genealogical and Historical Articles) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Enquirer, "The Lee Monument Ball," 16 Aug. 1877 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "The Nash Family in Virginia" by John M. Woodson, (1970) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - John Franklin Rixey: Memorial Addresses in the House of Representatives, February 25, 1907 and in the Senate of the United States, March 2, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - United States Naval Medical Bulletin, Oct. 1907 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings (miscellaneous articles on the Nash and Mills Families, death notice of Rev. B. Smith) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings (steamship and general advertisements and notices, ca. 1889) (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Documents
  - A Statement of Half Pay Claimed by Officers of the Virginia Line During the Revolutionary War (Doc. No. 17) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - A List of Officers of the Army and Navy Who Have Received Land from Virginia for Revolutionary Service (Doc. No. 30, No. 1) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - A List of Officers and Soldiers of the Illinois Regiment (Doc. No. 32, No. 4) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - A List of Armand's Corps from Virginia Entitles to Land (Doc. No. 34, No. 6) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Extracts from the Muster and Pay Rolls of the Virginia Militia of 1812 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Abstracts of Patents and Land Grants, 1607-1858 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Deed of Allen Taylor, 7 Oct. 1820, Botetourt County (transcript) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Marriage Bonds of: John Nash Read and Elizabeth Julia Spencer, John Cameron and Ann Owen Nash, and Robert Nash and Sabrey Redey; Indenture of Clement Nash, 1727-1805 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Wills of: Amy Nash, probated 14 Mar. 1710; William Nash, probated 4 Feb. 1718; John Nash, probated 12 Mar. 1870; Abstracts of Nash Family Deeds (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Wills of the Nash Family, 1686-1796 (includes 9 wills) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Will of Thomas Cowles, probated 9 Mar. 1853 (transcript copy) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Wills, Marriage Bonds, Administrators Bonds of the Nash Family, 1747-1793 (transcript copies) - Wills of John E. Nash, Elizabeth Nash, and Jeremiah Nash; Marriage Bonds of Nathaniel Nash and Darkes Fryer, William Nash and Elizabeth Spilman, John Nash and Molly Reynolds; Granting administration of Robert Nash's will to Richard Arrowsmith (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Abstracts from York County Court Minutes, 1718-1725 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Map of Virginia and West Virginia, 1887 (102)